So now let's go ahead and create
our first Amazon RDS database instance.
So on Databases on the left-hand side,
you can just click on Create database.
Okay, so when we are on the screen
we have to select the database engine.
So we have six engines types,
and we have two database creation methods,
would be standard create or easy create.
Because I wanna show you all the options,
we're going to choose standard create
which is going to be longer
but we'll show you all you need to know for the exam.
Now for the engine options,
we have Aurora that we'll deal with later on,
MySQL, MariaDB, PostgreSQL, Oracle,
and Microsoft SQL Server.
For simply sake, right now I'm just going to use MySQL
and go down with it.
We going to use the version
that is provided right here, MySQL 8.0.28
but whatever is the first selected is good enough for you.
Next, we have templates to meet our use case.
So if you wanted to have a free tier setup,
you would click here
and this would pre-select some options for the free tiers,
or if you had a dev test environment,
then it would pre select option for dev test,
and production, you have full control over every option.
Now I'm going to use production as a template
but we'll modify every option to be within the free tier
but I'm showing you this so that we can have a look
at all the options one by one.
So first for availability and durability.
We have three options.
We have Single DB instance, Multi-AZ or Multi-AZ DB Cluster.
So, because we want to remain within the free tier,
we're going to use Single DB instance
but if you want to have a standby database instance,
you would use a Multi-AZ type of option.
Now for the DB identifier, we're going to use database-1.
The credential is admin
and the password I'm going to use,
a password here that I'm just going to enter as we go.
Okay, next for the instance configuration,
this is the size of the underlying EC2 instance.
So in that case, we can have standard classes
or memory optimized classes or burstable classes.
And within it, you can choose whatever instance
that you want with different characteristics.
Now to remain within the free tier,
I'm going to use a burstable class.
I will include previous generation classes
and choose db.t2.micro, which is within the free tier.
Now for storage type, if you are in production,
you're going to use an Io1 type of EBS volume,
but as we run within the free tier,
I wanna use a gp2 type of volume,
which is lower performance.
And we'll use, maybe 10, 20 gigabytes of allocated storage.
Now we can also enable storage autoscaling
which will automatically increase
the size of the EBS volume
in case we are starting to near a threshold.
And what is the maximum amount of storage we want
in case we enable autoscaling, let's say 1000 gigabytes.
Now for connectivity, we have the option
to connect what was called an EC2 compute resource.
So this is in case you wanted to make sure
that there is connectivity
between a specified EC2 instance and your RDS database.
You would just choose it in this list.
And then the configuration in terms of networking
will be done automatically.
So you don't have to handle security groups
et cetera, cetera,
which is very helpful when you're a beginner.
But we're going to look at all the options.
So I'm going to say don't connect
to an EC2 compute resource.
Therefore we have to deploy in a specified VPC
and then we have to specify a subnet group
and then whether or not we want public access
to the database.
So I'm going to say yes
because I want to access this database from my own computer.
Next, we need to choose or to create a security group.
So I'm going to create a new security group.
And the name is going to be demo-database-mysql.
In terms of AZ preference, we could set one, but no need.
And as you can see, the port to connect to the database
on MySQL is 3306.
In terms of database authentication,
we have three mechanism.
The first one is to a username and password,
this is what we'll be using,
but we can also enable IAM database authentication
to have IAM users and roles directly access RDS,
or we can enable Kerberos,
but right now I'm going to leave it
as password authentication.
We can enable monitoring
and enhance monitoring gives you a 60 second granularity
on your resources, but I can disable it right now.
And we can specify some additional database configuration.
So for the initial database name,
I'm just going to enter mydb.
Then we can enable or disable backups.
So backups are automated
and we can have a backup retention period of 1 to 35 days.
And if I said zero
then it will just completely disable them.
So let's leave it at seven.
And then for backup window,
we can choose a specific time window
where the backups will be done, or no preference.
Then we can export the logs into CloudWatch Logs.
For example, you can export the audit log
from RDS into CloudWatch Logs for long-term retention.
Then do we want to have a maintenance window
for the minor version upgrades?
And if so, what is a window you want have?
And do you want to have deletion protection?
This is to protect the database
from being accidentally deleted.
So now, as you can see we have some DB cost of $17 per month
even though I told you this is within the free tier.
So it's not reflected right here,
but if you use a db.t2.micro type,
then you will have a free tier for this
even though it says here 17.34 US dollars.
So when you're done, just create this database.
So while my database is being created,
let's go ahead and download SQL Electron.
And this is a SQL clients
that we're going to use to connect to our database.
So very simple, you're going to click on Download GUI
and then click on it,
take the latest version for whatever platform you have.
So you have latest Windows
and then for Mac is going to be a DMG.
So I'm gonna do this one,
then open it and install it.
Okay, so my database is now created,
took a little bit of time.
And now, cause we can see it is available.
And so what I'm going to show you are a few options.
So first of all, we have the endpoint right here
and the port 3306,
and it's linked to this security group,
and this security group if you click on it
and look at the inbound rules,
we can see that we have an inbound rule here
on TCP port 3306.
So that's great.
Coming from just my IP address.
Okay.
So you should course modify this security group
if you have problem connecting to your database instance
to maybe have it to anywhere IPv4.
Okay, so now let's take this endpoint
and we're going to connect to it using SQL Electron.
So using SQL Electron I'm going to add a new database,
I'll call it RDSDemo.
It's a database of type MySQL.
And then for the server address,
I'm going to enter what I have right here on port 3306.
The user is admin and the password for me was password.
And then the initial database is mydb
as I entered it from before.
Let's click on Test
and the connection is successful.
If it's not successful, please have a look whether or not
your database was set to be a public database number one,
and number two, have a look at your security group settings
to make sure that your IP is allowed in.
So let's save this and connect your database.
And now I am connected into my database directly to mydb
which was the database that was created.
And in here I could go ahead
and enter some create table statements.
So CREATE TABLE mytable,
and then just a name of VARCHAR 20
and first name of VARCHAR 20.
So it's just a very quick statement,
just to show you how SQL works,
but this is definitely out of scope for the exam.
Execute this.
So now we have mytable that has been created
and then we don't have any content in it.
But you could have an insert statement
to insert some data into your table.
So you would say, for example, enter the value maarek
and then the value here, Stephan.
Execute this.
And then if you click on select throws,
then you see that my table has my name
and my first name to be maarek and Stephan.
So this is how you would use a RDS database with MySQL,
but again, out scope of the exam,
I just wanted to show you the full picture
of using SQL Electron.
So back in here, my RDS database is fully managed.
So this is great. We can use it.
This is amazing.
Other things we can do that are worthy
are to create a read replica
directly from this database
so we can create a read replica.
And then this read replica would allow us
to have more read capacity for our database
which would be very, very helpful.
And we want whether or not that database
to be Multi-AZ for recovery purposes.
So I'll keep it as No and cancel it next.
We can have a look at monitoring
and monitoring for example show us the CPU utilization.
And as we can see while the utilization is monitored
by my database, and we can monitor this,
for example, for scaling our database
if in case we have too many connections into it.
We can have a look
at the database connection accounts as well
to see how many clients are connected into our database,
and a lot of metrics overall.
Other things we can do with RDS is around creating snapshot.
So you can take a snapshot and this will snapshot database
and you can restore it wherever you want.
You can restore to a point in time for your database
or you can even migrate a snapshot
if you wanted to migrate a snapshot
into a different region, for example.
So all these are a bunch of options that we can use
but as we can see, the whole power of RDS
is to manage the database for us to have read replicas,
Multi-AZ, we can increase the instant type
as we go along and so on.
And that's all comes very handy
from a managed service perspective.
So you've seen all you need to know for your RDS database.
I hope you liked it.
And just to finish yourself,
please make sure to delete the database.
So to delete it, first you need to remove
the termination protection.
So you go to modify
and then at the very bottom, you will scroll down
and find the delete protection setting.
So here it is.
We'll disable it.
Press Continue.
And then Apply immediately.
And then once the delete protection is done,
you can go ahead and delete this database.
You can remove creating your final snapshots
and then say delete me
and acknowledge the fact that upon deletion
everything will be lost.
Click on Delete.
And you're good to go.
So that's it for this lecture.
I hope you liked it.
And I will see you in the next lecture.