So let's go ahead and now
create an Aurora database.
So I'm going to choose Aurora as of standard creates
and we'll see all the different options.
So as we know the additions, we have two possible additions.
We have Aurora MySQL, or Aurora PostgreSQL.
I will use Aurora MySQL.
And then from this, we have filters
in terms of different versions of Aurora.
As you can see they're available here and what they support.
So for example
if you wanted to have a global Aurora database
you could only use one of these versions.
If you wanted to have the Aurora databases
with a parallel query feature as well
it would filter this list.
And if you want to have versions
that support serverless 2.20
then you have these two versions of Aurora MySQL.
Obviously they may change for you
but you have the idea.
So to keep it simple
I'm going to use the default version
associated with this which is Aurora MySQL 2.10.2.
Okay.
Next, we have a template.
So templates represent how you want to create your database.
I'll use production to have the maximum amount
of details again.
So we choose database-2 for the cluster identifier
and here again, I can enter a password and a password.
Okay.
Next for the instance configuration
we can choose different kinds of instances.
So we have the memory optimized classes
or the burstable classes.
So no matter what Aurora is not part of the feature
but I can choose, for example, db.t2.small
to reduce my cost as much
as possible or a db.t3.small.
It doesn't, it's the same.
Okay, so let's use db.t2.small.
Next for Multi-AZ and durability.
We know that the data by default is going to
be Multi-AZ and durable, but it's possible
for you to actually create a Multi-AZ deployment
by creating an Aurora replica
or a reader node in a different AZ,
which is good for fast fallover and high availability.
So I am going to create an Aurora replica.
It's going to cost more money
but I can show you different features.
If you wanna follow along, you can decide not to
if you want to spend less money.
For connectivity I will not connect
to an EC2 compute resource.
And again, we want to have public access, yes.
And then we can choose an existing security group
for example, which is the demo-database-mySQL
or we can create a new one,
even easier demo-database-aurora.
Okay.
And as we can see, it's still using MySQL.
So the port is 3306.
Authentication for database.
We have either password or IAM based authentication.
I will disable enhance monitoring.
And then for database name, the initial will enter mydb.
So let's scroll down.
We have backup retention between 1-35 days
and you cannot disable it.
And then we can enable encryption.
We can have backtrack to a specific point in time.
And we can set up up to 72 hours.
We can send the audit log, for example
into Amazon CloudWatch logs.
And then everything is similar to what we had from before.
So let's just go ahead and create this database.
So my Aurora database is created and as we can see
we have a regional cluster
with a writer instance and a reader instance.
So here, the important fact is
that we have different instance to write and to read from
and they're in different AZ.
So this is the whole power of Aurora.
So if you click on database-2
as we can see to connect, we have two endpoints
we have a reader endpoint and a writer endpoint.
So these endpoints are very handy
because they represent an endpoint that will always lead
to the right writer instance.
And this endpoint will always lead
to the right reader instance.
So these endpoints is what your application
should be using to connect to Aurora.
But if you were to click directly
on this specific instance right here
this instance will have also a dedicated endpoint.
And that instance over here would also have
a dedicated endpoint once it is being created.
So it's all being in the creating space.
Okay.
So we have these features that are cool.
Then we have other features, so we can add more readers
into our reader cluster to add on with scaling capacity.
And we can also create a cross-region read replica
if you want to have a replica in another region.
We can restore any point in time.
And another one is that we could add Replica autoscaling.
So this one is very important because, well
we can create a policy and this policy would say, Hey
based on the average CPU utilization of your Aurora Replica
or the average number of connections to your Aurora Replica,
then scale your read replicas.
So say, read replica scaling policy and say, okay
I want to make sure
that my read replica stay at the target value of 60%.
And if I go over, please create more read replica.
We could also define a scaling period
for the scaling policy, which makes sense.
And what's the min and the max capacity.
So one up to fifteen Aurora replicas.
And this is very handy to
have read replica autoscaling as a database.
So I cancel it.
We don't need it right now.
And now I've made sure that
both my dead points database and end points are available.
So we're good to go.
So one last thing I can do to show you the whole power
of Aurora is to do action and add AWS region.
And this is only possible if you chose a version
of Aurora that was enabled with the global database feature.
But here we can add the database region to other regions
and this will allow you to get a global Aurora.
Now you can see this is not possible with this cluster
because we need to have an instance
with a compatible size to do this first.
So we need to change the instance, for example
to a large type of instance.
And then we would be able to add other regions
to the database cluster.
But anyway, I wanted to show you the feature right here.
Okay.
So that's it for Aurora, this is pretty much what you get
which is an amazing database with amazing performance.
Great, great scaling capacity global and so on serverless.
So really, really complete database.
I really like this offering from AWS.
Now to be done with this hands on
just take this database and you want to delete it
but as you can see, it's not available.
So what you need to do first is to
delete the reader instance.
So type in delete me
then you need to delete the writer instance.
So again, action, delete, and then you type delete me.
And then once both these things are deleted
you are going to be able to delete your whole cluster.
So I will wait when it's done.
That's it.
My database is now deleted
and I will see you in the next lecture.