So now let's discuss
advanced concepts of Aurora
that you need to know going into the exam.
So let's talk about replica autoscaling.
So let's say we have a client
and we have three Aurora instances right now.
So one will be writing through the writer endpoint
and the other two will be reading
through the reader endpoint.
Okay, now let's say that we are having
many, many read requests on the reader endpoint
and so therefore, the Amazon Aurora databases
have an increased CPU usage.
In that case, we can set up replica autoscaling
and what this will do is
that it will add obviously Amazon Aurora replicas
and then what will happen is that
automatically the reader endpoint
is going to be extended to cover
these new replicas and therefore
these new replicas will start receiving some traffic
and the reads will be happening
in a more distributed fashion,
hopefully bringing down the overall CPU usage.
So this is replica autoscaling.
The second thing is custom endpoints.
So let's say we have the same setup,
but this time we have two different kinds of replicas.
As you can see, we have some DB.R3 large
and some DB.R5 2X large.
So some read replicas are bigger than others.
And the reason you would do this is
that you want to define a subset
of your Aurora instances as a custom endpoint.
So let's say we define a custom endpoint
on these two bigger Aurora instances.
The reason we would do so is for example
that we know that these instances are more powerful
and therefore, they're going to be better
to run analytical queries on these specific replicas.
So when you do so,
you have a custom endpoint that's defined.
And when you have a custom endpoint,
generally the reader endpoint itself
is not used after defining custom endpoints.
So it would not disappear, but you would not use it anymore.
And what you would do in practice,
in like practically speaking,
is set up many custom endpoints
for many different kind of workloads,
therefore allowing you to query
only a subset of your Aurora replicas.
Next we have serverless.
So this is going to give you
automated database instantiation
and auto-scaling based on actual usage,
which is great when you have infrequent,
intermittent or unpredictable workloads.
And therefore, you don't need to do any capacity planning.
You're going to pay per the second
of each Aurora instance that is being spun up,
and this can be a lot more cost effective.
So how does that work?
Well, the client is going to talk to a proxy fleet
that is managed by Aurora,
and in the backend, many Aurora instances
will be created based on your workload
in a serverless fashion.
So you don't have to provision capacity at all in advance.
Next, we have Aurora Multi-Master.
This is when we want continuous
write availability for the writer notes.
So what does that mean?
That means that in your Aurora cluster,
every Aurora instance is a writer node.
That means that every Aurora instance can take in writes.
And so this is different from a normal Aurora cluster
while you have one new master
and in case it fails,
then a new one is promoted as the new master.
So here your clients can maintain
multiple database connections to multiple Aurora instances,
and if one was to fail,
then your clients can write
to another Aurora instance and you'd be good to go.
Finally, we have Global Aurora.
So in case we have a Aurora cross region read replica,
it's going to be very helpful for disaster recovery.
Very simple to put in place,
but you can also set up the Aurora Global Database,
which is the recommended way of doing things today.
In this case, you have one primary region
where all the reads and writes happen,
but you can set up up to five secondary read-only regions
where the replication lag should be less than one second
and up to 16 read replicas per secondary region.
And this will help you decrease latency
for the read workloads all over the world,
but also in case you have a database outage in one region,
promoting another region for disaster recovery purposes,
has an RTO, so recover time objective,
of less than one minute.
So it takes less than one minute
to recover into another region.
And here is a sentence you should look out for
from an exam perspective.
It takes, on average, less than one second
to replicate data across region
for your Aurora Global database.
So this is something that if you see an exam,
it's a hint to use a Global Aurora.
So let's have a look.
We have US-East-1 as our primary region
which is where the applications do the read and writes,
and then we'll set up a secondary region
in EU-West-1, where some replication happening
with a global database of Aurora
and the applications that it can do
read only from that setup.
But in case US-East-1 fails,
then we can fail over to EU-West-1
by promoting it as a read-write Aurora cluster.
Aurora also has an integration
with machine learning services within AWS.
So the idea with Aurora Machine Learning
is that you can have ML-based predictions
to your applications, you have the SQL interface.
It's a simple, optimized and secure integration
between Aurora and different AWS machine learning services.
So two supported services are SageMaker,
which allows you to use
any kind of machine learning model in the backend
or Amazon Comprehend if you want to do sentiment analysis.
Now, you don't have to be an expert
in SageMaker or Comprehend.
You just need to know that Aurora
has an integration with those.
So in order to use Aurora Machine Learning,
you don't need to have machine learning experience.
And the use cases for this would be to have
fraud detection, ad targeting,
sentiment analysis, or product recommendation
all within Aurora.
So to give you the architecture idea,
Aurora is going to be connected
to the machine learning services in AWS.
And your application can just run a very simple SQL query.
For example, what are the recommended products?
Aurora will send some data
into the machine learning services,
such as, for example, the user's profile,
the shopping history, et cetera, et cetera.
And then the machine learning service
will return a prediction directly to Aurora.
For example, the user should buy a red shirt and blue pants
and then Aurora can just return the query results
to the application all through as a result of the SQL query,
which is very handy.
So that's it, just a feature you need to know
going into the exam.
So that's it for this lecture.
I hope you liked it
and I will see you in the next lecture.