Let's talk about Amazon ElastiCache.
So the same way you get RDS
to have managed relational databases,
ElastiCache is going to help you get
managed Redis or Memcached
which are cache technologies.
So what are caches?
Well, they are in-memory databases
with really high performance and low latency.
And what the cache will help you with is
to help reduce the load off of databases
for read intensive workloads.
The idea is that the common queries are going to be cache,
and therefore your database will not be queried every time.
Just your cache can be used
to retrieve the results of these queries.
What this also helps you do is
makes your application stateless
by putting the state of your application
into Amazon ElastiCache.
And because we have the same benefits our RDS,
AWS will take the same maintenance
of the operating system, the patching,
the optimization the setup, configuration,
monitoring, failure recovery and backups.
Now, if you use Amazon ElastiCache
just so you know that it will require you
to do some heavy application code changes
for your application.
This is not something just enable
and off you go, you have a cache.
You need to change your application to query the cache
before or after querying the database.
And we'll see the strategies in a minute.
So now let's talk about
the architecture for using ElastiCache.
And there can be many, but I'm just giving you an example.
So, let's say we have Amazon ElastiCache
and RDS database and your application.
The application will query ElastiCache
to see if the queries are already being made.
And if it has already been made,
and it is stored in ElastiCache,
then it's called a cache hit.
And then it just gets the answer
straight from Amazon ElastiCache.
And we were saving a trip
to the database to do the query.
Now, in case of a cache miss,
then we need to fetch the data from the database.
So we're going to read it from the database.
And then for other application or other instances
where the same query will be made
we can write the data back into the cache
so that such as the same query next time
will result in a cache hit.
The idea is that it will help relieve load
from your RDS database.
And because you're storing data in the cache
there must be a cache invalidation strategy
to make sure that only the most current data
is used in there.
And this is the whole difficulty
around using caching technologies.
Another architecture is around storing the user session
to make your application stateless.
So the idea is that your user will do a login
into any kind of your applications,
and then the application will write the session data
into Amazon ElastiCache.
Now, if your user is redirected
to another instance of your application
then your application can retrieve the session cache,
the session directly from the Amazon ElastiCache
And therefore your user is still logged in,
and doesn't need to log in one more time.
And so the idea is that
now you made your application stateless
by writing the session data
of your user into Amazon ElastiCache.
So if we compare Redis and Memcached, what do we have?
Well, for Redis, we have Multi AZ with Auto-Failover,
and we have Read Replicas if you wanted to scale the reads
and have high availability.
So this looks a lot like RDS.
We have data durability using AOF persistence,
and we have backup and restore features.
So again, Redis is all about data durability.
And feature wise as a cache,
it supports sets and sorted sets
which are keywords you can also look for at the exam.
So here I'd like to show Redis
as a cache that gets replicated
that is highly available and durable.
Whereas Memcached is using multi-node
for partitioning of data.
So it's called sharding.
There is no high availability,
there's no replication happening.
It's not a persistent cache.
There is no backup and restore.
And this is a multi-threaded architecture.
So we have multiple instances altogether
working in Memcached with some sharding.
So the idea here that you need to remember
is that Redis really is here
for high availability, backup, read replicas,
this kind of stuff.
Whereas Memcached is a pure cache that's distributed
where you can afford to lose the-
You lose your data, there's no high availability,
and there's no backup and restores.
So these are the main differences that you're going to have
between the two technology.
So that's it.
I hope you liked it,
and I will see you in the next lecture.