Okay, so let's go ahead
and practice using the ElastiCache service
by creating our first Redis database.
So let's get started,
and in this we have the option to create a cluster.
It can be either a Redis or a Memcached cluster.
And I click on Create cluster.
We'll just go ahead with the Redis cluster setup.
You can have fun and look at the options for Memcached.
So this is the cluster creation UI,
and we're going to Configure and create a new cluster,
but we could Restore from backups
if we had created backups from before.
Now we have the chance to either enable the cluster mode,
and this is to have multiple replications happening,
and it's going to enhance scalability and availability,
or to disable it.
And you'll have a single shard, a single node group.
And you have maximum one primary node
and up to five read replicas.
To keep it simple and to keep it free,
we'll disable the cluster mode.
Next, Cluster info, so demo-redis.
Then the location,
so whether or not we want this ElastiCache service
to be on the Cloud or on your premises,
thanks to the service called AWS Outposts,
we'll keep it simple,
because we don't have On premises anyway,
we'll use the Cloud.
Whether or not we want to be Multi-AZ,
so Multi-AZ will provide you enhanced high availability
through automatic failover to a read replica, a cross AZ,
or in case of a primary node failover,
that will disable it, okay?
And the reason I do so is that
because we would pay more otherwise,
and we're just going through the demo
of creating an ElastiCache cluster anyway.
And this Auto-failover enables you to get high availability
by failing automatically to a read replica
in case of a primary node failover.
I can keep it as is for now.
The Cluster settings,
so we specify the Engine version.
The Port, we'll leave everything as default.
The Parameter groups as well as the Node type,
so this time the Node type is way too high for our needs,
so we can use a micro type of cache, okay?
And I'll use a t2.micro,
because I know it's enough right here,
but I guess the other ones may be as well.
Number of replicas is between zero and five.
So what's happening is that if you have two replicas,
then, of course, you're gonna be
in a Multi-AZ kind of settings, okay?
But if you set up zero with replicas,
then Multi-AZ cannot be enabled,
and so you have these options completely disabled,
and that makes sense, right?
So we wanna be again with a node right here,
so I will not have any replicas
so we'll leave the number as zero.
Next we need to create a subnet group,
which is a collection of subnets, okay?
So I'll call this one my-first-subnet-group.
And this will tell the ElastiCache service
to run the nodes within the subnet group.
So we'll choose our main VPC, default VPC,
and we already have three subnets created
and selected by default.
And then click on Next.
We can enable Encryption at rest using a key
if you wanted to,
as well as Encryption in transit if we wanted to.
And then if we do enable Encryption in transit,
then we can get some Access control,
so we can specify use Redis AUTH for user access
in which you would specify a token in here.
And that token could be used to connect to the cluster.
But I will disable it.
And next we can go into Backup,
so you want to Enable automatic backups or not
on your database.
I will disable it.
Maintenance windows, to perform the upgrades
as well as the backups.
Logs, Tags, so it is very similar to RDS,
you will notice.
So everything is created,
let's go ahead and create our ElastiCache node,
and there's only one,
so it's a cluster of one node right now.
My ElastiCache database is now created,
and I can click on it,
and if I had an application that I wrote
with some code,
I could actually use the Primary endpoints,
or if it was a read replica, a Reader endpoint
to allow to read from my cache, okay?
Now, there is no easy way for me to show you
how to connect to a Redis cache,
because it's not that easy
and you need to actually write some code.
And that would be too complicated.
But from an AWS perspective,
from this console, you can see all the details
as well as Nodes, Metrics, Logs, Network Security,
and so on.
And it looks just like RDS,
because, yes, it is very similar service to RDS,
but it's intended for Redis and Memcached.
So the last thing you have to do
is take this Redis cluster, Action, and then Delete.
And then, do you wanna backup?
No, you just type the name of the cluster, Delete.
And you're done with this hands-on.
Okay, that's it.
I hope you liked it,
and I will see you in the next lecture.